William Claire Collection Relating to Alan Swallow
William Claire Collection Relating to Alan Swallow
1942-1990
Claire, William F.
0.5 linear ft.
Two copies of Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, edited by William Claire, along with a collection of material pertaining to the creation and production of the book, including correspondence, manuscripts, galleys, reviews, notes, clippings, etc.
4592162
Biographical History
Alan Swallow (1915-1966) was an American professor and publisher. A graduate of the University of Wyoming (1937) and Louisiana State University (1939), he taught English at several universities before becoming the founder and owner of his own publishing firm, Alan Swallow, Publisher. As publisher, he focused on poetry and fiction of contemporary writers, both well-known and lesser-known; he also published several collections of his own poems.
William Claire was the founding editor and publisher of the literary magazine Voyages, a Yaddo and MacDowell scholar, and a Rockefeller Foundation resident in Bellagio, Italy. His essays and reviews have appeared in over 50 major publications. [Adapted from Georgetown University's finding aid for the William F. Claire Papers.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Claire Collection Relating to Alan Swallow consists of correspondence, printed material, writings and a small amount of miscellany, all pertaining to Claire's Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow.
Correspondence includes letters to Claire from Jene Lyons (publisher) and Robert Dickey (founder of Poetry Bag), as well as photocopies of letters from Swallow, presumably for use in Claire's book.
Printed material consists of two copies of Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, along with the manuscript, galleys, and reviews.
Writings contains writings by Swallow and about Swallow, some of which may have been used in the book. All are either eprints or photocopies.
A small amount of Miscellany completes the collection -- a photocopy of one of Swallow's catalogs, a typed list of the book's proposed contents, and a few others items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by name or topic.
Related Material
See also the
Alan Swallow Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Biography; Literature -- American Poetry; Publishing, printing and book arts; Claire, William F.; Dickey, R. P. (Robert Preston), 1932-2002.; Lyon, Jene.; Pauker, John.; Stanford, Ann.; Swallow, Alan, 1915-1966.; Alan Swallow, Publisher.; Lightning Tree, Inc. (Santa Fe, N.M.); Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow: some letters and commentaries / edited, with an introd. by William F. Claire.; American literature -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Poets, American.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Poems.; Authors.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2015.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Dickley, R. P., 1975 (Box 1)
  - Lyon, Jene (Lightning Tree Inc.), 1973-1976; 1986-1987,; 1990 (Box 1)
  - Pauker, John, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Princeton University Library, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Schevill, James, 1968 [?] (Box 1)
  - Stanford, Ann, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Swallow, Alan, 1948-1951; 1963,; undated; photocopies of letters used in Publishing in the West (below) (Box 1)
  - Swallow, Mrs. Alan, 1967; by an attorney on her behalf (Box 1)
  - The Swallow Press, 1968; undated (Box 1)
  - Wagner, Durrett, See The Swallow Press.
  - Yueh, Norma, 1968; includes letter to Anaïs Nin (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, first name only, A-Z, undated (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Book reviews, Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, [1974] (Box 1)
  - Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, early manuscript, with working title "Some Letters of Alan Swallow" (Box 1)
  - Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, galleys (Box 1)
  - Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, 1974; hardcover (Box 1)
  - Publishing in the West: Alan Swallow, 1974; softcover (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, newsletter, undated catalog of Alan Swallow, Publisher, Swallow's obituary (Box 1)
- Writings
  - About Swallow (Box 1)
    This folder contains essays, articles, and poems by Gus Blaisdell, Cleanth Brooks, [Robert?] Chrisman, J. V. Cunningham, Richard Elman, Vi Gale, Mark Harris, Weilliam Hogan, Lewis Nichols, Prairie Press, Bobbi Sherman, William Stafford, Jim Wood, and Norma Yueh, as well as Swallow's obituary. All items are either photocopies or reprints.
  - By Swallow (Box 1)
    This folder contains the following: "Story of a publisher," "The tenth year: An editorial," Yvor Winters: A publisher's comment," "Epitaph" (excerpt from letter to friend), and an interview of author Vardis Fisher. All are photocopies, no originals.
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous handwritten notes (Box 1)